he's on trt since a few years and his
wife says um since he's on testosterone
he started snoring at night and she even
recorded him it's very loud and but he
is not obese at all not fat nothing he's
not a bodybuilder with a thick neck
nothing so would there be any connection
between snoring and testosterone even in
a not fat
guy so people have reported both an
improvement as well as an exacerbation
of both snoring as well as sleep apnea
and it seems
to kind of be a hit or miss depending on
the individual some people improve some
people worsen um I personally cannot
think of a particular concept or or or
mechanism that would cause it with the
exception
of um somebody who has a broader neck or
somebody who has a Lar your chest
potentially maybe increases in volume
initially due to some weight gain from
water retention and then ultimately in
the long term possibly additional muscle
training um you know people always
consider training and weightlifting as
something that is good something that is
is healthy and it is but we have to
understand that BMI does not
discriminate between fat and muscle body
mass index or a larger person is going
to have some sort of conditions develop
over time that somebody would a smaller
BMI is not going to have one of those
impacts is cardiovascular health on the
heart because the heart now as a pump
has to pump to more tissue so even if
you're muscular and you're a larger
person your heart health is going to
suffer negatively for it secondly is the
ne circumference in America for example
the uh standards for primary care where
they say assess for sleep apnea is a NE
circumference of 16
in and that is not a very large neck by
today's standards a lot of men have
necks over 16 in so if your next
circumference increases whether it's
from weight lift excuse me whether it's
from weightlifting or just you know
being
overweight your more susceptible to
sleep apnea and or snoring um but a lot
of times snoring is not just related to
obstruction in the in the neck or the
chest uh it could be a deviated septum
so it could be anecdotal I I I just
don't know the true answer of why it
happened to this individual but I have
heard from patients both hey this has
gotten worse as well as this has gotten
better but everything I just mentioned
is just my own hypothesis and why this
can be I just don't see un unless
someone can point me to any literature
any any any ideas as to why I don't see
any connection between breathing and
testosterone